<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An help to the duty in, and right improvement of sickness. By Henry Newcome, M.A. minister of the Gospel</title>
            <author>Newcome, Henry, 1627-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27347</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828563</idno>
  <idno type="VID">173134</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240883483</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing N897</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216847</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828563</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99828563e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27347)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173134)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1955:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An help to the duty in, and right improvement of sickness. By Henry Newcome, M.A. minister of the Gospel</title>
                  <author>Newcome, Henry, 1627-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Parkhurst at the Bible and Three Crowns in Cheap-side, near Mercers-Chappel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: An help to the duty of right improvement of sickness.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">God --  Wrath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173134:1"/>
            <p>AN HELP TO THE DUTY IN, And right Improvement OF Sickness.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Henry Newcome, M. A. <hi>Minister of the Gospel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurst</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheap-side,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:173134:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173134:2"/>
            <head>To his Beloved Friends, the Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Manchester,</hi> in the County <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>GOD hath broken the Health of the Nation, in making a sad and sore Sickness <hi>Epidemical.</hi> And he hath made some very sad Breaches upon us by it. It is <hi>his</hi> hand, and he ought
<pb facs="tcp:173134:3"/>to be seen, and acknowledged in it, so as I am sure he is not. But when his <hi>hand is lifted up, they will not see, but they shall see,</hi> Isa. <hi>26.11.</hi> It is a thing to be lamented, (and more than to be lamented, if we knew what that was that we could do to remedy it) That this Judgment is so little observed, and so unconcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly undergone, and passed through so unprofitably, in respect of the Spiritual use of it. And I grieve heartily to see so many Sick, and in Pain and Sorrow; but more, that so few are at all better by it, or offer at all at any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of it. Certainly, Gods Judgments must be accounded for; and if we generally be so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned,
<pb facs="tcp:173134:3"/>his Controversie with us, shall not fall thus. And it will be sad, if ever our Lot fall to be under his hand, when he shall punish us, <hi>yet seven times more</hi> for our Sins, <hi>Levit. 26.18.</hi> There is a sad and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable unprofitableness under Gods <hi>Ordinances.</hi> I know not but that God may offer to carry on his design upon mens Souls, by <hi>afflicting Providences;</hi> and nothing more like, than by Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that comes so near to us. That as God said in another case, <hi>If they will not believe, neither hearken to the voice of the first sign, they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the voice of the latter
<pb facs="tcp:173134:4"/>sign,</hi> (Exodus <hi>4.8.</hi>) One would think if the former way of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be not believed, the voice of the second Sign in personal Application (to their Pain and Cost) by Sickness, should be hearkened unto. But there is neither voice, nor hearing. <hi>God hearkens and hears, but they speak not aright; no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents of his wickedness, saying, what have I done?</hi> (Jeremiah <hi>9.6.) Every one</hi> [bruitishly] <hi>returns to his course, as the horse rusheth into the battel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been affected with this, and upon this occasion have had thoughts on this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb facs="tcp:173134:4"/>out of a real zeal against the woful security of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent time. And since I have no opportunity to serve the Souls of men by Preaching, I thought to adventure for once, this way, before I dye, to speak to those whom I love, and seek their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal good, whom otherwise I cannot possibly come at. And if it reach further than where I am known, I know it may be nothing but what is needful, and God may bless it to many that are, or have been afflicted this way. I do not plead in Excuse for Publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing these Papers, That they were extorted from me by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertunity of any: For I have
<pb facs="tcp:173134:5"/>not had opportunity (as they are now digested) to Preach them to any. And if there be any fault in Printing this, I take it upon my self, and am willing to undergo the censure, whatever it is, out of a desire to do good to those that need it. I am sure, in these sad Circumstances that we are in. I shall count it a small matter to be scorned and slighted by any, if I may do good but to one afflicted or unafflicted Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>I am sensible, others of more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, might have the advantage of their Parts and Names, to have done the work better. But who
<pb facs="tcp:173134:5"/>can tell but this may find some ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, as it is so sincerely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and may provoke some one of a better Head, and Heart, and Pen, to take up the Subject, and set it off for more general ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance? And if it attain but this end, I shall not account my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture ill made.</p>
            <p>I confess, <hi>My flesh trembles for fear of God, and I am afraid of his judgments,</hi> Psal. <hi>119.120.</hi> It may be, by this time this gets Published, the Distemper may be abated. I pray God it may. But however the Discourse will not be unseasonable; For <hi>the great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Sickness, is most after Sickness.</hi> And as I am sure many
<pb facs="tcp:173134:6"/>will be found to have suffered by it, so I am as sure that too many of them have not profited by it, as they should have done. So that if the Sickness be done, the Duty of men on that account will be found undone. And besides, this may help us, against God begin again with us; or being faithfully practised, may prevent in some mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, the return of the Judgment. And the things practised on this account, are never unseasonable. What men would see should have been done, when they come to dye, are as good to live with, as to dye with.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173134:6"/>
            <p>God hath in a little time dealt severely with us in these parts, in a remarkable Circumstance of his hand; In removing so <hi>many eldest Sons,</hi> and some <hi>only Sons</hi> and Heirs to Estates and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. <hi>This rod hath a voice in it, and the man of understanding may know</hi> the matter, <hi>Mic. 6.8.</hi> The Death of the first Born broke the hardned <hi>Pharoah.</hi> God will give to the truly humbled, that wait upon him, in the way of his Judgments, <hi>A better name than that of sons and daughters,</hi> Isa. <hi>56.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And may not we of this Town fear and repent, on the condsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
<pb facs="tcp:173134:7"/>of the sorest of Sickness (called <hi>the Sickness</hi>)? An emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Minister born amongst you, and that lived and died in the service of your Souls, hath left in some Papers of his, which I have seen, That you might lye at the feet of the wisest <hi>Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel,</hi> to learn the meaning of this Dispensation, that for three times together, at the forty Years end, the Plague hath raged in this Town. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with you the last Plague, and you are now within a part of a year of the fourth fortieth Year. I am sure it can do you no hurt, to fear lest it should keep the time with you; and
<pb facs="tcp:173134:7"/>I doubt not, but you know you are ripe enough for it. But what if you set your selves, every Person and Family, to cast away your iniquities, and to prepare to meet God, that God may pass you by at this time? And it may do much to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, if you would do as much to prevent it, as you would be glad to do to remove it, if it were come upon you: And you would not lose your labour if the Judgment should not come. <hi>I do not desire the woful day, the Lord knows,</hi> Jer. <hi>17.16.</hi> I pray for the good of the place, which I wish well to, above any place in the World, and do desire the eternal
<pb facs="tcp:173134:8"/>welfare of every Soul of you; and am on that account above all, in all sincerity.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>October 13. 1684.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant, <hi>HENRY NEWCOME.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173134:8"/>
            <head>An Help to the DUTY OF Right Improvement OF SICKNESS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Job 5.6, 7, 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Altho affliction cometh not forth of the dust, nor doth trouble spring out of the ground:</p>
                  <p>Yet man is born unto trouble, as the sparks flie upward.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I would seek unto God, and unto God would I commit my cause.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1-55" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <hi>ELiphaz</hi> doth in these words, (however mistaken in <hi>Jobs</hi> case, and so did not speak of God <hi>the thing that was right,</hi> Chap.
<pb facs="tcp:173134:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173134:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:173134:10"/>42.7.) give excellent counsel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our carriage under affliction; namely, That we should look unto God as to the rise of it, and to him alone for relief.</p>
               <p>In them are two parts;</p>
               <p n="1">1. The considerations to lead to the Duty, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The duty it self, <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>The consideration under affliction to lead to our duty is, That afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth not come fortuitously or accidentally, as if it <hi>rise out of the dust,</hi> and came blindly, and of it self upon us, as weeds that grow out of the earth without any plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ploughing, or sowing for them. They may come we <hi>know not how,</hi> as to the Physical next cause, but not we <hi>know not why,</hi> as to the moral cause of them. Man <hi>is born</hi> (indeed) <hi>to trouble, as the sparks to flie upward;</hi> not <hi>made</hi> to trouble, (as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173134:10"/>hath been well observed) but <hi>born</hi> to it: As born, he is born in sin, and so born to sorrow; and tho every man is afflicted one time or other, in one kind or other; and men may think, they have but their share in the common heap of the troubles of the life of mankind; yet this comes not of it self neither, it comes not blindly and promiscuously, but is ordered, and measured out in every circumstance of it, in wisdom and proportion; and therefore God is to be applied to in the case, whatever it is, as coming by his appointment for our sin, and for some great end upon us. If it were my case, as it is yours, (says this Wiseman) I would speedily turn unto Cod, and look at him as the chief and supream or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer of the whole; and I would in the way, by him appointed, commit my cause wholly to him, and that should be my chief business and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, in this sad and sorrowful affair.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:173134:11"/>
               <p>I shall content my self with this one Observation from the Text, (tho it would afford many) as sutable to my design in our present condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is a matter of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment for every man, to have a right apprehension of his affliction, in the true progress of it, as it respects God and his soul, in the causes and designs of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Afflictions come not of themselves, but they are sent, and they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and ordered every one of them; they come from God, and to him we must apply our selves, both in, and after them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>For publick evils; Is there any evil in the city, and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> Amos 3.6. <hi>Who gave Jocob to the spoil, and Israel to the robbers? did not the Lord, he against whom we have sinned?</hi> Isa. 42.24. It seems the very spoilers and robbers did not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:173134:11"/>serve themselves, nor primarily set on themselves, but <hi>Israel</hi> was given to them by God, and for their sins. And the <hi>men of the world,</hi> that any where invade their neighbours, and disturb their peace, are <hi>Gods sword, Psal.</hi> 17.13.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. For <hi>particular personal affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> they also are appointed for us; <hi>wearisome nights</hi> (says <hi>Job Chap.</hi> 7.3.) not onely befalls me, but are <hi>appointed</hi> to me. No sorrows come upon us, but the Lord bids them come against us, no instruments can set themselves on work.
<note place="margin">Isa. 10.15.</note> The <hi>Saw</hi> or <hi>Ax</hi> may be sharp, but cannot do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing without an hand or arm to weild them.</p>
               <p>To instance in <hi>Sickness,</hi> (to which I shall chiefly apply my self in this discourse.) These sad distempers come not of themselves, not from the earth, tho infected, and sending out unwholesome and poisonous va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours; the Lord ordered it to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173134:12"/>pregnant with them to such an effect. It is not the infection of the air, the sudden changes from hot to cold, that does it; for who ordered that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature, or could order it, but the Lord of all? And besides, suppose that these should be causes, they are but made use of by the supream Lord and Master of them all; and it is evident, they are ordered, and particularly directed, because they are not thrown out promiscuously: some are taken, and others are left; some escape in the most epidemical sickness, and some escape death that are sick, when others die that were under the same symptomes and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of them that have escaped. So that the <hi>whole dispose of this lot that is cast,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pr. 16.33.</note>
                  <hi>is of the Lord.</hi> He is to be acknowledged chiefly, and our applications should be made to him, both <hi>in</hi> and <hi>after</hi> our great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:173134:12"/>
               <p>Now this makes affliction quite another thing, and leads into thoughts of another kind, and puts upon other measures. I fall sick of this or that sickness, why this is from the Lord.
<note place="margin">Ex. 15.26. Job 33.19. 2 Sam. 12.15.</note> The Lord hath sent it, the Lord hath <hi>put upon me</hi> this disease. The Lord hath <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sited me with this pain.</hi> The Lord hath <hi>stricken</hi> my Relation, or my self. The Lord, when people fear not his <hi>great and fearful Name,</hi> doth threaten, (and also doth do it) to make their plagues <hi>wonderful,</hi> and the plagues of their pride, <hi>even great plagues, and of long continuance;</hi> and <hi>sore sicknesses, and of long continuance,</hi> Deut. 28.59. <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>sore</hi> in their kind, and of <hi>long continuance;</hi> to tarry long in a Countrey or place, or hang long on the persons afflicted, <hi>as ours do;</hi> this is from the Lord.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a great thing to consider, <hi>that God should be concerned about
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173134:13"/>me,</hi> tho it be but to afflict me. That I should on a sudden fall into his hands; <hi>It is a fearful thing to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the living God,</hi> Hebr. 10.31. out of whose hands I cannot quit my self, and none can rescue me. It may beget great and aweful thoughts to be doing with, that he hath done it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>He delights not to afflict.</hi> He is infinitely good, and gracious, and merciful,
<note place="margin">Psa. 35.27.</note>
                  <hi>He takes pleasure in the prosperity of his servants.</hi> And if their state would bear it, he would have them always in health and cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and all to succeed well with them. <hi>He doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men,</hi> Lam. 3.33. And therefore there is something more in it, than I am willing (it may be) to see, or find, when so good a God doth thus treat me. When <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> (I think it was) was told by some flattering tell-tale, that such a one exclaimed of him;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173134:13"/>he bad them enquire diligently, for some ill thing had been done; for he was a good man, and if not greatly injured, he was sure he would not speak ill of him. And so sure, some great ill has been done by me, or so good a God would not thus afflict me, and so sharply testifie against me. A proper reflection for a good man under sickness.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>There is no way out, but by the same hand that we came in,</hi> Hos. 6.2. He can heal as well as wound, and bind up as well as bruise. If he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to prison, there is no one else can discharge me; and therefore to him I must apply my self for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and to none else.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Sin is the provocation:</hi> and that must be searched for, acknowledged, and amended, Psal. 107.17. <hi>Fools because of their transgression, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of their iniquities, are afflicted.</hi> And it is in the case of sickness, as the next words shew. Few, but they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173134:14"/>may say, if they had not been <hi>fools</hi> and <hi>sinned,</hi> but they might have kept their health. It is a special time to see sin, and it is the pardon and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that which our disease must go off by. It is repentance by which we make our peace; <hi>to return to him that smiteth. Surely it is meet to be said unto God, I have born chastise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I will not offend any more; that which I see not, teach thou me; if I have done iniquity, I will do no more,</hi> Job 34.31, 32. This is <hi>seeking unto God,</hi> and <hi>unto God to commit your cause.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note>
                  <hi>The sorrow after God worketh repentance.</hi> Let all the indignation turn upon the sin that hath brought this evil upon thee: And by this, 1. Thou shalt be assuredly helped to bear thy trouble. 2. Thou shalt in likelyhood get out of it, and it may be soon. 3. And assuredly get good by it.</p>
               <p>USE. First, See hence, <hi>how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173134:14"/>and carnally most people go through their sickness.</hi> God is not seen in it, nor sin seen by it. Men are sick, and either,</p>
               <p>First, They talk, <hi>they have catcht this new disease,</hi> and this is from the unwholesome weather, or an effect of the late Comet, and the extream frost, and the unwonted drought that followed it. Or I have catcht it of such a one, or I catcht cold, and so have brought it upon me; all this may be true; yet this is piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful common talk. God is not seen in all this, nor named by some from the beginning to the end of their whole sickness. Or,</p>
               <p>Secondly, Their whole discourse is, <hi>how they are held and handled,</hi> where their pain is, and how it works them. And a story they can make of all passages, as if nothing else was minded by them. And they spend their time in groaning and complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173134:15"/>and in using means to get up a gain. Or,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Never <hi>think but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover again;</hi> as if recovery were due to the sick, and must come in course. After a few days, and the sooner the better, I hope to be revived again, and to be on my feet again. Now this is a great question; Death hath come in at a less window than this. And besides, if this sickness comes from God, there is something else to do, than just to overcome as if it were going to the prison, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out again, and to pay nothing. It is odd reckoning at this rate, as if either, 1. God had not done it; or 2. had done it without cause; or 3. had not the right on his side, and had done the too hard; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 4. had retracted his Action, and would let it fall thus, and would suffer a Nonsuit. Can any thing be thought more disparaging to the blessed Majesty, the Holy, and Wise,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173134:15"/>and just God? <hi>Is there evil in the city, and shall not the Lord do some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what?</hi> (as some read that place, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6.) Shall he not make something of it, to the conviction of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? Never think it. Or,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, When <hi>men are never se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in sickness, unless they think they shall die.</hi> As if they would stand out against God as long as they can, and keep their sins as long as is possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Men would not be in any fault, as the cause of their sickness; and will keep their ground, and be as they were, and after recovery be so too; unless apparent danger force them to other thoughts. And we find oft, that men are <hi>not sick enough,</hi> to have the Minister sent for, or to be prayed with. Alas, to repent onely when they think they must not live, makes it very suspicious, whether they sincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent or no. And besides, it may be death as soon as apprehended, and so prevent all endeavours to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173134:16"/>thee to God; that thou that wilt not do it, till thou fearest death, mayest die when thou fearest, and so have no time to do it all. An usual thing it is to say, he never suspected himself till last night, or this morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and if he applyed not himself to God, till he suspected himself, he was ill advised, and would be sadly provided for his dreadful change. O the deceitfulness, and wretched wickedness of mens hearts! They love their sins, and would not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease themselves, nor dislodge their sins for <hi>sickness,</hi> but for <hi>death</hi> they would; thank them for nothing. And it is sadly to be feared, that such as will not think of repentance, till they think they shall die, do not think truly to repent at all; but that it is repentance with pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, and that if they revive they will sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. As a man does by his goods on his sick-bed, he disposes of them so and so; but if he live, he will have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173134:16"/>them himself. As if such a wretch should say in his heart, If I die, and can sin no longer, then I am sorry for my sin; but (as if God could be mocked) they resolve it is with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of revocation; and if they live, the dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yed sin shall live too. This is to slight sickness, unless mortal, and God too in it; and thus too too many do, and so come to die in their sins. And here I may say, It were a very desirable and advisable thing, that men would think of dying continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and use themselves to serious discourses of death in their best health, and so consult about this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair with the wisest: That to talk of death, and Christ, and the Soul on a sick-bed, should not be counted <hi>rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and an ill sign, because it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what he hath always used, and his sickness now quickens him to it. And if we could <hi>use</hi> our selves more to such converse; to speak of death to the sick, might not speak
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173134:17"/>a suspicion of death, and so discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the sick party. And be sure you speak betimes, that it be not driven till you cannot speak to them, and they want that help it may be to die with; and you be troubled after, that you said so little to them.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, When <hi>men give way to crosness and peevishness in their sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> That those that have the pains and trouble of them, have this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to it, that they cannot please them with any thing they do. Not that I would have any discouraged hereby, in their willing attendance and pains about the sick; for God may design the sickness of one, to be a correction to more than one; pain to the party, and toil and patience to Relations to attend upon him. And besides, they know not how soon they themselves may need the pains and patience of others in the like case. But however it is a great miscarriage to be peevish and humor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173134:17"/>it looks as if you were angry at your cross, and none can please you that are about you. It might tame and meeken you in all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, if you were sensible of Gods hand upon you; and whilst you have him to please, who seems to be offended with you; one would think it might be less difficult to please you. Some interpret, that of Eccles. 5.17. <hi>All his days he eateth in darkness, and he hath much sorrow and wrath in his sickness;</hi> of a carnal wretched Miser, that hath no comfort in what he has, <hi>eats all his days in darkness,</hi> hath no joy in his very meat, for the cares that continually feed upon him; and when such an one comes to be sick, he is vexed and fretted that he is taken out of his business, and he is in anger in his sickness, and frets and rages at his pain, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint, and danger of death. And
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173134:18"/>thus oft sickness works the wrong way: God is not seen, or thought on, or men would be of another temper.</p>
               <p n="2">2d. USE, To answer this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>How should we carry under sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.16.</note> To be sick (as the Apostle says to <hi>suffer</hi>) as a <hi>Christian;</hi> as one that sees God inflicting it upon him for his sin, that acts wisely, <hi>and seeks to God,</hi> and <hi>unto God commits his cause.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First, <hi>Feel thy affliction.</hi> Take heed you slight it not,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.5.</note> nor <hi>despise it,</hi> so as not to seek for help, or repent, unless in extremity; not sick enough to be prayed for: as if repentance was never seasonable or intended, unless we must die. Surely there is a frown in this rod. It is a sad hand of God that is upon us. Sickness in it self is a sore pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173134:18"/>to nature; it is sad to them that feel it; To be thrown into the dark, and shut out from business and company, and to have pain and distemper to be taken up with. When a man is <hi>chastned with pain upon his bed, and the multitude of his bones with strong pain; so that his life abhorreth bread, and his soul dainty meat;</hi> (or as Psal. 107.18. <hi>His soul abhorreth all manner of meat.) His flesh is consumed away that it cannot be seen, and his bones that were not seen, stick out.</hi> [If it be a good sign of recovering, yet it is a sad punishment in it self, and an expression of Gods displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, to lose all flesh and strength on this fashion, and to have a body to begin again.] <hi>His soul draweth near to the grave, and his life to the destroyer,</hi> (Job 33.19, 20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) And then also to be at the gates of death, and to say, <hi>the sorrows
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:173134:19"/>of death compassed me, the pains of hell gat hold upon me; I found trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and sorrow,</hi> (Psal. 116.3.) When thou mayest say as <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> did,
<note place="margin">Isa. 38.10, 11, &amp;c.</note>
                  <hi>I am deprived of the residue of my years, I shall not see the Lord, even the Lord, in the land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> [I shall go to Church no more, nor injoy opportunities for my Soul any more, which it is well, if I did so to purpose as I should have done; and if I must see the Lord no more <hi>in the land of the living;</hi> It is well if I have good hopes that I shall see him in the land that I am going to. Believe it, a great and tremendous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern!] <hi>I shall behold man no more, with the inhabitants of the world.</hi> [To whose company I have been all along used, and it is well if I be not too much glewed to it, and have sinned with; and be not an utter stranger to the new company I am
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173134:19"/>going to.] <hi>Mine age is departed, and is removed like a shepherds tent.</hi> [My acts and deeds of life are done, chuse what kind of age it has been; and whereas I vainly thought, I had had a well-built house to have tarried in; I find it is but a she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherds tent, a place for a poor shift, and to serve a Temporary turn; It's easily unpinn'd, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down, and removed utterly.] <hi>I have cut off like a weaver my life.</hi> [Like a web not half woven, I have by my sin cut it out of the loom.] <hi>He will cut me off with pining sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, from day even to night wilt thou make an end of me; I reckoned till morning, that as a lion, so he will break all my bones; from day even to night wilt thou make an end of me. Like a crane or a swallow, so did I chatter; I did mourn as a dove, mine eyes fail with looking upward. O Lord, I am oppressed, undertake
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173134:20"/>for me, and all this because of thine indignation and wrath: for thou hast lift me up, and cast me down.</hi> Psal. 102.10. These are sad, and proper resentments for a sick-bed. Do not carry under the least sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, as if there was nothing in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. It may soon be more, and too great for thee to deal with; and besides, it is a sign of a good child-like temper, to be checkt with a little. There may be much displeasure in a little:
<note place="margin">Le. 24.41.</note> Take it as <hi>a punishment,</hi> and <hi>accept of the punishment of thy sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Fall to thy duty early.</hi> Begin betimes the proper work for thy condition: Go out to meet him <hi>whilst he is yet a great way off,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 14.32.</note>
                  <hi>and desire conditions of peace.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the very siege if you can; however, stand not out to be storm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The sooner you apply your
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173134:20"/>selves inward, 1st. The work will be easier. 2dly. You will be more able for it. 3dly. The likelier to be sincere, when you do not stand out to the last. 4thly. You may fare the better, and less affliction may serve: This is taking the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease at the beginning, which is as safe for the Soul as the Body; bleed speedily, and purge speedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but especially repent at the beginniog of the sickness. 5ly. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you may be sure of help, to be patient, and have supports and comforts if the affliction increase, and continue long; if you begin on this manner. And 6ly. An hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py death, or an holier life. O take thy disease in time in this sense. To allude to that of (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.20.) <hi>Shimei</hi> acknowledges he had done perversly, and begs, that the King would not lay it to heart: for as he had been a great offender, so he was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173134:21"/>
                  <hi>the first</hi> of all the house of <hi>Joseph</hi> that came to meet him. It is a fine thing to come in at first, to bow with a little: such a one shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be overcharged, but either spared in the weight of his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, or favoured in his strength to bear.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Consider your ways.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, search, and try; hear what conscience says; now it is backt, and it may be will speak, and be free with thee: This is for such and such a sin, thus and thus hast thou done, or thus thou hast not done, which thou shouldest and mightest have done. <hi>For this cause many are sick and weak amongst you, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fall a sleep,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.30. Some miscarriages about holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (which thou canst seldome quit thy self from) may proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re God to afflict thee in this very kind.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173134:21"/>That forequoted place, <hi>Job</hi> 34.31, 32. is a most excellent form of words for such a time, but not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally to be used: but add to it, <hi>Psal.</hi> 139.23, 24. <hi>Search me, O Lord, and know my heart: try me, and know my thoughts, and see if there be any wicked way in me, and lead me in the way everlasting.</hi> It is not to ask God to know, as if he knew not, or to beg of him to take notice of what he certainly knows; but to make him know himself, and all his thoughts and ways, that he may be led into the way everlasting. Seriously think of thy ways, when thus corrected, for it is sin hath done all this.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Beg repentance and forgiveness.</hi> To be healed the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine way, is to be forgiven. No for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness of sin, no recovery, either at all, or to any purpose. Our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173134:22"/>Saviour heals with pardon, as if it could come effectually no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way. To say, <hi>Son, Thy sins be forgiven thee,</hi> is as much as to say, <hi>Rise up and walk,</hi> Mat. 9.2. It is as easie to say the one, as the other; and it is the sick mans interest, that the one should not be without the other. What availeth it truly, (if it could be) that my disease should go, and my sin that brought it, lye upon me undischarged? The Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist therefore prays, <hi>That God would look upon his affliction and pain, and forgive all his sins,</hi> Psal. 25.18. And when he blesses God for a recovery, it is first, and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the other; for <hi>forgiving all his iniquity, and healing all his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases,</hi> Psal. 103.3. And Isa. 33. <hi>ult.</hi> They <hi>shall not say they are sick,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Lord hath <hi>forgiven their iniquity:</hi> Either as a cause, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction to their healing, or as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173134:22"/>an additional mercy, the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their health; that they should be healed and forgiven too. O be loath to come off, (if thou could<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est) with recovery, and thy guilt still upon thee.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>Beg Soul, health.</hi> To be delivered, and advantaged against the power of sin by this affliction: <hi>That if thou hast done amiss, thou mayest do so no more,</hi> Job 34.32. I said, Lord, <hi>be merciful to me, heal my soul, for I have sinned against thee,</hi> Ps. 41.4. A true ingenious Soul, that is rightly sensible and awake, desires pardon before health; for it is better than health: For <hi>in his favour is life,</hi> Psal. 30.5. And <hi>his loving kindness is better than life,</hi> Psal. 63.3. I had rather have his pardon and peace, and lye sick, than be well and want it, or doubt of it. And secondly, I do equally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173134:23"/>grace and healing with my pardon. For a Soul truly changed, if it were possible to be forgiven, would be greatly unsatisfied, if left under the power and love of any sin: nay, if it could be assured to be forgiven as oft as he sins, he could not be content to live a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Such a principle the new na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is of, love to God, and likeness to him, that the true Soul <hi>would not sin,</hi> if in some <hi>sense he might;</hi> that is, might sin with indemnity. So in this case of sickness, the wise, good man, should be loath to come out unpurged and unhealed. He says, I hate sin, that causeth this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure; and I would be cured more than in the Temporary cure of sickness; It is death to me to be well, and sin again as I have done. And besides, it will hinder and retard my cure; my health may wait for my repentance, or it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173134:23"/>may bring me soon into some worse evil: The dregs of the disease un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purged, doth always bring some worse distemper, of which I count sin the worst; and if that remain, some greater evil will assuredly come upon me; and therefore cry mightily for a purified and purged heart at such a time as this; and let this be thy great care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment. <hi>He looketh upon man,</hi> [when sick] <hi>and if any say,</hi> [which all do not, God knows, but those that do, God looks at] <hi>I have sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and perverted that which was right, and it profited me not.</hi> [I have done basely and wickedly, and against all Justice, and Reason, and Right, and done my self no good; neither by any thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I have sinned against thee; for he that truly repents, hath this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his sin, That it is not only unlawful, <hi>but unprofitable;</hi> and if
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:173134:24"/>he be not convinced, that it is his interest as well as duty, he will never effectually leave sin;] now to this man will God look: he will <hi>deliver his soul from going into the pit, and his life shall see the light,</hi> Job 32.27, 28.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>Now consider death,</hi> which sickness leads to, and is part of, and learn to die by every sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; for some sickness will be that unto death, and prepare for this to be it; and put thy self into such Scripture-sentiments, as are menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the first direction.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>Apply thy self to Christ freshly and truly,</hi> who only can help about death: It is amazing and distracting to think of death, if thou canst not believingly think of Christ. This is one of the great things, that makes Christ absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:173134:24"/>necessary for thee. O get thy Soul near to Christ, by whom alone thou canst comfortably be sick, and profitably recover; <hi>For he himself took our infirmities, and bare our sicknesses,</hi> Mat. 8.17. Tho we did never read that he was ever sick, yet he took our sicknesses as his own, and had a compassionate feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with every sick person that was brought unto him; and did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in greater things, what was equivalent, and more evil than sickness; and hath taken the curse and sting out of every disease for us; and besides,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 2.9, 14, 15.</note>
                  <hi>hath tasted death for every man;</hi> by whom we are delivered from the evil and <hi>danger</hi> of death, and also <hi>from the fear of death.</hi> In <hi>Peru,</hi> they say, they have a plant, which they put into the hand of the sick person, which shews whether he shall live or die, and that as he looks cheerfully or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173134:25"/>sad upon it. We have no such plant to try by; but if Souls be helped to fix on Jesus Christ, and have him put into the hand of their faith, they must needs be cheerful; and it is a blessed presage, that they shall be for eternal life; but if he looks sadly upon Christ, and if he now help him not, for want of a true interest in him, he is like to die everlastingly. O he is a <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 33.23, 24.</note>
                  <hi>an Interpreter, one of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand,</hi> that at such a time as this, <hi>can shew to man his righteousness.</hi> [Gods Righteousness in his punishment; or can help the poor sick man to discover his sincerity, or rather the Righteousness of Christ to shrowd him in.] Then <hi>he is gracious unto him, and saith, deliver him from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down into the pit, I have found a ransome for him.</hi> [This ransome from Hell, and Death, and the Grave, is none but Christ; and he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173134:25"/>is valued as one of a thousand to the sensible sick man, that can be a Messenger of such tidings to him: Death (as a great Divine said) is <hi>a thing by it self;</hi> but it is not to be done <hi>by thy self.</hi> The Lord will help thee to die, when thou comest to die, if he help thee to live uprightly and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely whilst thou livest; that, as he said, <hi>When I come to do the work which I never did, I shall have the help which I never had.</hi> When one said on his death-bed, <hi>He would stick to Christ;</hi> one replied, But your surer hold will be, <hi>That Christ now will stick to thee.</hi> And indeed this is a sure comfort at such a time. That the Child in the Mothers arms, holds fast about the Mothers neck; but the Childs safety is, that the Mother holds fast on the Child: and so for the Soul at
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:173134:26"/>Death; Thou may hang by thy weak Faith on Christ; but he will hold thee faster than thou cast hold him, and this will secure thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> After this, <hi>frame to patience.</hi> This Sickness is from God, and for sin. <hi>Thou with rebukes doest correct man for ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> Psalm 39.11. This Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is Gods rebuke of me for my iniquity.
<note place="margin">Lam. 3.39.</note> And why <hi>should a living man complain, a man for the punishment of his sin?</hi> The thoughts of God in Sickness, do quiet by Diversion; they groan heavily, that have nothing else to do, nothing to think of, but their Sickness and Pain. <hi>Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> said, He had sometimes eas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himself under the pain of the Tooth-ach, by filling his mind with some excellent thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:173134:26"/>of the Imployment of his Soul. One in great pain, but of great Patience, said, <hi>He did not deliver himself to his pain, but to God that laid it upon him.</hi> A thankful patient Submission to the Divine Wisdom and Will in this case, is a great duty, and means of relief and present sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and the way to have real profit by the Affliction. <hi>Patience worketh experience,</hi> Romans 5.4. A man must be quiet and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with his Affliction, before he can get any <hi>Experience,</hi> or learn any thing by it. Which leads to the</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninth</hi> Duty; <hi>Get as much good as you can in the affliction.</hi> The expectation of good by the Affliction is a great help to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience under it; and therefore set thy self for it, all that ever thou
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:173134:27"/>canst: Be learning all along. Beg of God, that he will <hi>instruct thee,</hi> as well as <hi>chastise thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psa. 94.12.</note> Now is the time to know that of God, and Christ, and Sin, and the World, so as you never did before, and probably never had done, if not thus afflicted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly; Be much in prayer.</hi> Line thy Bed with Prayer. <hi>Then cryed they to the Lord in their trouble, and he saveth them out of their distresses,</hi> Psalm 107.19. It is seasonable in Sickness, as well as in a Storm at Sea. O, what words may you take with you in this case, out of <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s prayer, and <hi>David</hi>'s prayer, Psalm 116, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That God would be merciful to you, and heal your Soul. For mitigation of pain, for necessary Intermission, and refreshments; for strength to bear,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:173134:27"/>for patience, for recovery, if God see good; and for eternal Life if you dye, and to live to better account, if you do recover. But this leads to the</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>ƲSE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How we should carry after af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions?</hi> Tho the Sickness be gone, yet if God sent it, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be done more than to get rid of it. And the truth is, the <hi>great benefit of sickness is to be reaped after sickness. Hezekiah</hi>'s writing, wherein he profitably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects upon the passages of his Sickness (<hi>Isaiah</hi> 38.9.) was made when he had been sick, and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered of his sickness.</hi> For if God sends it, and inflicts it, and for sin, and for thy future good, it is your part and duty to see to the full improvement of it. For if we recover, to be the same,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:173134:28"/>or no better, or worse, what were we afflicted for? It might have <hi>risen out</hi> of the <hi>dust</hi> or <hi>ground,</hi> and go to the dust a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, for any use thou makest of it, toward God or thy self. But hath God, the Wise, and Holy, and Good God, taken thee, and thrown thee on a Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, laid thee alone, and in si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence so long, laid thee so long by as useless, and shewed thee this, and the other World, and all for nothing? Doth he give Physick to come away, as it came, and bring nothing away with it? Shall he bring such a grievous evil upon thee, and (as was said before, from that of <hi>Amos</hi> 3.) Shall he <hi>not do something?</hi> Consider—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> It is a choice and spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial season of learning much.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:173134:28"/>Some great Divines have said, they have learnt more of Christ on a Sick-bed, than by the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of their whole Lives. Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is a great instructor. It will tell you that, and make you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it too, which all other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structors could never do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is a sign of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterately diseased Soul, if the Bodies sickness doth not stir it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This unconcernedness under thy bodily Sickness, will either be Death to the Soul, or another Judgment to bring thee to rights: For God will not lose his Rod upon thee. <hi>As yet exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est thou thy self against God,</hi> said <hi>Moses</hi> to <hi>Pharoah, Exodus</hi> 9.17. And to the recovered man our Saviour says, John 5.14. <hi>Sin no
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:173134:29"/>more, lest a worse thing come unto thee;</hi> there is certain danger to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee. Therefore</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> If thou hast not been sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, and helped, and kindly mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted under thy affliction; but hast been common and ordinary in thy frame all along; be humbled for thy great sin and hardness: Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how ever thou hast gotten through. But do not think to come off thus; to be but as thou wert before, after all. Resolve upon it, that there is more work behind, for something must be done for this Affliction sake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> If thou hast been sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible and melted; labour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, pursue and increase that frame; keep it, and make it move: what was but hinted then, get the whole of it now thou
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173134:29"/>hast health again, and strength to pray, and think, and labour, which it may be then thou couldst not do.</p>
               <p n="1">1st. <hi>Observe to hate and contest the sin that then reflected upon thee.</hi> When he hath them in the Cords of Affliction, then he shews them <hi>their work</hi> (what work they have made on it) and <hi>their transgressions that they have exceeded.</hi> If it were a sin then, let it be one now, and so dealt with by thee, that it may never come upon thee at such a time again. The <hi>sin that went just before.</hi> The <hi>sin that came first to mind.</hi> The <hi>sin that came hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est to light, after most painful en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry.</hi> The <hi>sin that did lye then most heavy upon thee.</hi> O hate this sin, and pray against it, and never allow it the grace
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:173134:30"/>and connivence with thee, that it hath had. <hi>See thy sins of omis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> and be resolved upon more painful Godliness than ever heretofore; for thou hast learn'd, thou mightst have been ruined <hi>for not doing.</hi> Retain the same thoughts against the same things, and make them stronger, and let them not pass off, as the thoughts of that time extorted from thee by thy extremity, as an act done in duress, that is in it self with thee invalid. Oh with what rage, and without mercy, will such thoughts tear thee, when they come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain on the like occasion!</p>
               <p>Resolve in health to perform the resolutions made in Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
               <p>Offer to God the Ransom of thy Life, in the Sacrifice and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:173134:30"/>Death of the Sins which thy Sickness apprehended and brought to thy hand for thee. And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this, To repent in health, as you did in Sickness: Make good your Sick bed-repentance, that you may prove it sincere. And take heed that you never fall into the case that I have heard of one lately, who being Sick after a former Sickness, had this woful complaint; I was Sick, and I repented of my Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and I thought I did then repent truly; but I sinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and now I think I repent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; but I cannot say, it is more than I did then; and the effect shewed <hi>that</hi> was not sincere; and how shall I trust to this Repentance now? And he was forced away in this condition.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:173134:31"/>
               <p n="2">2ly. <hi>See the emptiness of the world, and the mischief of sin.</hi> And let it be always to thee, what it was in Sickness. <q rend="margQuotes">O says one, Sickness is the Mother of modesty; on a Sick-bed a man is neither Lustful, nor Covetous, nor Ambitious; he is sick, and all the World is sick too; as when a man is giddy, all turns round with him.</q> It is a time for God to withdraw men from their [vain worldly] purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and to hide pride from man, <hi>Job</hi> 33.17. Happy (says one) is that man, from whom his pride is so hid, that he may never find it again. What did any of these things avail thee? I was Sick, I would have given them all for a little health; much more now I would give them, and Health, and all, for a glimps of Gods favour now, and when I dye. How mortified should I be to the World from
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:173134:31"/>henceforth? for it is just worth as much and no more to me now, than it was to me when I was sick.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. <hi>What you could not do for sickness, that you found needful to be done, do it now with all serious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and diligence, as if God had restored you for this very end.</hi> If thou cryed, <hi>O spare me a little, that I may recover strength before I go hence and be no more,</hi> that thou mightest have a little respite to be better fitted against thou must dye indeed, see thou make it good, now God hath heard thy Prayers, and seen thy Tears. It was poor imperfect distracted work, that thou then madest of it; do it better now, and think thy life given for that very end, and be thankful and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:173134:32"/>
               <p n="4">4ly. <hi>How precious should Christ be to me, and his Covenant: he and it are all my salvation, and all my desire.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.5.</note> There is my comfort and refuge. This is my Cordial against sinking, and swooning, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and despairing on a Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. <hi>His name is as ointment poured forth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 1.3.</note>
                  <hi>to them that believe he is precious,</hi> 1 Peter 2.7. O let my Soul ever love, and prize, and admire him, as I saw cause then to do; he is always the same; O that I could always keep the same sense of it.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>Inward peace should be my great care.</hi> If I had it then, O what Joy and Relief was it unto me? And how easie did it lay my Sickness: O let me stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to cherish and keep it, and value it above all comforts in the World. If I wanted it, what
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:173134:32"/>a darkness was it to me? How did it imbitter my Sickness, my unassuredness about my Soul? Why God spared me to recover this strength, sent me back to get this lesson better; hath given me to live to make this matter readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               <p>It is very sad for poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to cry out for the light of Gods countenance, when they are in distress and afraid of Death; and when the fit is off, to let the pursuit fall, and not to miss it at all. Poor Soul! if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou wantest it, be never quiet till thou hast it in some measure. <hi>Give all diligence to make thy calling and election sure;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> that thou mayst have Peace, and <hi>mayst be found of him in peace,</hi> 2 Peter 3.14. Pray for it to him, who alone can give it;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:173134:33"/>remove all the sin and neglects that do lett your comfort, and wait for it, as that which thou canst as ill be without in thy Life, as at thy Death. And if it be not neglected, and thou fail not on thy part, whilst thou goest on,
<note place="margin">Isa. 50.10.</note>
                  <hi>Obeying the voice of the Prophet</hi> [keeping out of sin, and keeping up to thy duty in all things.] <hi>Tho thou walkest in darkness, and hast no light; yet trust in the Lord, and stay thy self upon thy God,</hi> and thou shalt have peace and safety at last. It is not peace barely wanted, but neglected, that can make thy condition dangerous. O let poor Creatures think with themselves, That if they had dyed of such a fit, what a dangerous case they had been in; let their recovery be taken for such a Mercy, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is, and let them take
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:173134:33"/>heed they be not as unready the next time. And if another can say, I found comfort in my Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and if I had died then, I should have had good hopes; And what doest thou live to make thy case worse, and less assured? God forbid.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>Conclude with thy self, That he hath not recovered thee, and made thee to live, that thou shouldest not dye.</hi> Say, I must dye sometime. It may be I have escaped, when I look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it, and may go when I do not look for it. O let this always live in thy thoughts; be dead to Sin, and the World, that there may be less to dye from, when thou shalt be Sick unto Death. What so oft at Death, and no fitter for it! O
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:173134:34"/>pray, and strive to dye daily, and to live as a Sojourner, and Stranger, the rest of thy time.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>Take hold of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life.</hi> Thou wert lately hard by it; O never forget it; think of that blessed State on the other side of Death. And <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the hope of the glory of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.2.</note> That you are turned back to be tossed again; but you shall come to shore one day, and never be tossed more. O! what a blessed Place, and Rest, and Peace, and Holiness, and Love, thou hast been in sight of! Long for it, when thou shalt be dead for good and all, and must dye no more, to be happy; when thou shalt be with <hi>Christ, which is far better,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:173134:34"/>Philemon 1.23. <hi>When you shall for ever be with the Lord,</hi> 1 Thessalonians 4.17. Entertain and comfort thy self, <hi>and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with these words:</hi> Mighty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per converse for those that have been Sick. And</p>
               <p>Eightly, <hi>Let all this be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in expression of your thankfulness to God.</hi> Acknowledg his bounty and goodness to thee; O love the Lord, that hath heard the voice of thy Supplication, in the day of thy Trouble, when thou didst call upon him. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the Circumstances of thy reviving, the signal passages of thy Recovery. Something may be gathered up, that is remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able from every Sickness, which may ingage thy love, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thy trust in God for the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:173134:35"/>time to come, <hi>Psalm</hi> 34.1. to the 7th, and <hi>Psalm</hi> 116. from 1st to the 9th. <hi>Sacrifie to God the sacrifice of thanksgiving, and call upon his name with rejoycing: Pay thy vows.</hi> Offer to God (as one says) the ransom of thy Life. Thankfulness is the best preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Health.</p>
               <p>O let your lives be mortified, and humble, and spiritual, and heavenly; you have seen the Grave, live as such, more exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary in your lives; that if <hi>you have known any thing after the flesh, you may henceforth know it so no more,</hi> 2 Corinthians 5.16.</p>
               <p>But to Sin still, or to be worse, and more secure, because thus spared, is the highest ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:173134:35"/>and the greatest hazard you can run. <hi>Having received such a deliverance,</hi> as this, <hi>should we again break his commandments?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezr. 10.13.14,</note> It is (says one) like striking the Chyrurgion with one hand, who hath cured the other for him. God forbid (as the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> hath it, <hi>God forgive</hi>) God forgive such security, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and ingratitude, and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limate wickedness, and prevent the woful end that is like to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall such as are guilty of such a sin.</p>
               <p>IV. <hi>ƲSE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is to such as are yet free from this sickness.</hi> Is there nothing for them to do?</p>
               <p>First, <hi>Remember what you have had at any time this way.</hi> You
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:173134:36"/>have, it's like, been Sick some time. Others Sickness may call to your rememberance what you have suffered in the like kind, and also whether you profited and mended by it. And see with care and fear, whether the vertue and profit of it be not worn off, and that you be not ready to be Sick again. If the old mark be gone, we must at it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Think not that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers need or deserve more than you,</hi> that you are spared. Are they <hi>greater sinners than you? I tell you nay, but except you repent, you shall</hi> [be Sick also and Dye,
<note place="margin">Luke 13.2, 3.</note> and] <hi>perish</hi> too.</p>
               <p>Make every ones Sickness yours, to do them good, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:173134:36"/>your selves good by it, till you come to have a Sickness of your own to be instructed by.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Do as much to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent as to remove it;</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve your health, as to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it; come in of your own accord, when you see others of the same Tenure forced in. Take their Circumstances to heart, and apply thy self to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and serious Holiness, that thou mayst not need this Rod, or at least mayst be better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to entertain and improve it, than they could be, that are made examples to thee. It is a sad time when so many are Sick, and Religion so dead as it is. Oh, that it might be a time of reviving as to that!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56-112" type="pages">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:173134:37"/>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>ƲSE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is of Observation and Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to several cases, that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from one another in this present Concern. Since this Affliction is from God, it is good to consider how wise and punctual he is in his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence this way: How he suits the Circumstances of men; at least they ought to take it so.</p>
               <p>First, <hi>Some may be sick, that have little to do.</hi> Such have leasure to be Sick.</p>
               <p>Some indeed have less to do than they would have.</p>
               <p>Some have less to do than they should have.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:173134:37"/>
               <p>For the former, God may call them to <hi>perfect the work of their patience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 1.4.</note> now the active part of their life is gone; and if they can behave themselves brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that, they shall honour God and their Religion greatly; it may be more than ever they did by working; and they shall find sweetness in the exercise of their Grace, and shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded for their patience as duly as for any work they ever did for God. If a man overlive his parts and ability for work, or his opportunity for work; God will maintain his old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, tho sick on their bed; they were weary of their uselesness, and complained they wanted work, and God sends them work; they have time to be sick, and have nothing to do but to attend to it
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:173134:38"/>with patience, and to an holy improvement of it towards God. It is <hi>cheap dying,</hi> (as a great man said) in such circumstances; and this is wisely ordered by God for you.</p>
               <p>Others are sick: why, better be sick than idle; they would find nothing to do, take to no business, throw themselves out of all useful imployment: It is just with God to lay them to bed: better be sick, than lead an idle fudling life; and less will maintain it, and it may prove more wholesome to you: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess it is sad for such to be sick, when they come not fairly by their sickness.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.32.</note>
                  <hi>Yet God may judge them, and chastise them, that they may not be condemned with the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:173134:38"/>
               <p>God may make you know, how you spend your time, and punish your misexpence of it, by filling your mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s with pain and sorrow. Many Wretches that have said, <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we die;</hi> have eat and drunk, and to morrow, or in a little time do die upon it. O the destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Souls, and Estates, and Comforts of Life, and Life it self, that excess and idleness have made amongst us! It is a true observation, and a sad one, That our new drunkards, generally, live not so long, as the old drunkards did; God makes the poison to work sooner: and if a young man will be dissolute, ordinarily he is soon gone: that he that would do nothing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy his life, should live but a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:173134:39"/>while. Such unprofitable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons as these, Is it not justly and wisely done, that they should be laid under sickness? It is better for Relations to see them sick, than to see them sin, as they use to do: They may know now where to find them, and not have them wanting at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonable times, as they were wont: And God may bless sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to the health of their Souls; God hath sometimes made a long sickness, contracted by no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a course, to bring some to Repentance, and to detest their ways, and their Companions and good fellows; and to resolve to live otherwise, if they might live.</p>
               <p>God oft for the terror of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is pleased not to trust
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:173134:39"/>them, but takes them away; but he causes them to bear Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony against the way they lived in; and it calls aloud upon all that survive, to break off their sins by Repentance; that they may escape sickness, or at least Repenting before sickness, they may better know that their Repentance is true; which is hard for a man to know that it is so, when he comes not in till forced, and cannot tell on what principle he Repents;
<note place="margin">Eccles. 7.17.</note>
                  <hi>If you will destroy your selves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time,</hi> we cannot help it. But yet we are encouraged in the ways of God, from this, That the stoutest of you when you come to be sick, and fear death, (unless surprized by the suddenness of it) you utterly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim your whole course. And
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:173134:40"/>some love not the sight of their drunken companions, when they come into that condition. And the truth is, such Panders for the Devil, (for I can call them no better) who have seduced others to sin, if they were sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of the dying curses that some of their convinced compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions have left upon the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, they would have little joy of their lives, unless they spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Repented. And we think it is as good to stay where we are, as to fall in with you, and come back again when we come to die. O that young men would be wise,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.1.</note> and consider, and <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their Creator before the evil days come, wherein they shall find no pleasure:</hi> and <hi>that</hi> from the great wickedness of their lives, which yet have been so little a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:173134:40"/>time. Let all despisers of <hi>Christ,</hi> speedily seek unto him, lest that be verified of them, which <hi>Christ</hi> said in a like case, (John 7.24.) <hi>Ye shall seek me, and shall not find me: and where I am, you cannot come:</hi> nay, in the state you are, you shall never come.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Some are sick that are too busie.</hi> Over head and ears in the World, and busier by far than they should be; why, God justly takes them off, and makes them find time to be sick. They could not find time to pray, or hear, or keep Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; but God finds them time to be sick. And it may tend to cure their immoderacy towards the World, and then they will be great gainers. However they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:173134:41"/>are justly dealt with in their present suspension; and they had better lye by it to the work of Repentance and patience all their days, than to be trusted with health again, to be so unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully busie in the World as they were. Our blessed Lord, together with his most earnest caution, to <hi>take heed</hi> lest at any time, [if it were but one time, it were too many by one] <hi>your heart be overcharged with sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting and drunkenness;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 21.34.</note> joins with these, [as matter of the same sin and danger] to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharged <hi>with the cares of this life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The heart may surfeit of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares, and these eat out Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and bring decays upon the Soul. How have some good
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:173134:41"/>men seen the snare of too much business? And how have others resolved, they would not let a Trade master them, but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with what their Trade would bring in, without taking up their time from reading, and all duties that might improve their Souls, tho they could have had a far fuller Trade than they had? And others, that have known when they have had enough, and have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn themselves from such a throng of business, and have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven place to others that had less. But others will toil, as long as they get any thing; and the more they get, the more they toil. Now it is an act of mercy to send a good fit of sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, to give such a man some respite from his toil: And God
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:173134:42"/>may bless it, to cure his heart of his Sinful and Destructive thirst after the World, to the rescue of his Soul. And let such be thankful for Gods care of them, and improve their Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to the cure of their Souls on this account.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Some are laid aside by Sickness, <hi>That had little rest, and must be busie for their own and Families necessities.</hi> They lived on their hard labour, and but barely could live with all their toil: and yet oft these must be Sick too. This is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a sad case, and yet very frequent. But the Wise God doth order it for great and good ends. The poor man may want time to mind his Soul, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Eternity as he should do, and must be Sick to do it.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:173134:42"/>Alas, their Sickness is no rest to their toil, tho it be a res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite from it; but the greater is their patience, and submission to the Divine Will, and their trust in the Divine Providence. And let such Repent of their sins, and turn to God with all their hearts, to provide for theirs, that are now taken out of their hands, and put into Gods own. And let them that are Gods Stewards, and have of Gods Riches in their hands, look to it, that they lose not such an opportunity of Disbursement, to relieve the destitute Families of such as <hi>are Sick,</hi> and were <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious</hi> when in health. God certainly has provided you with an overplus for such a time as this. <hi>The poor shall never cease out of the land; therefore I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:173134:43"/>thee, saying, Thou shalt open thy hand wide unto thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to thy poor, and to thy nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the land.</hi> (Deut. 15.11.) To <hi>thy poor,</hi> and to <hi>thy needy;</hi> they become <hi>thy</hi> care and <hi>thy</hi> charge under God, who hath made thee able, and has laid his command upon thee. And in such an advantaged object of mercy as this, let him refuse the Divine command for mercy and bounty, that dare.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, God makes <hi>Sickness general,</hi> without respect of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> or <hi>parties;</hi> Rich as well as Poor; City and Town as well as Countrey; Old as Young; and it enters upon us without dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.14.</note> This is Gods wise hand, <hi>to the end that man should find out nothing after him.</hi> That all
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:173134:43"/>should fear God and his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and mend upon it. If none were Sick or dyed, but the Ancient, the young ones would be vain and secure. If none dyed but the young, the men of age would be uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. But the voice of this Providence cryeth to all,
<note place="margin">Mic. 6.9.</note>
                  <hi>Hear ye the rod, and him that hath appointed it.</hi> None can secure himself in this day of the Lords Visitation. And God is to be seen and acknowledged in this proceeding, on this particular account; That tho we are wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully broken by divisions, and severed sinfully into Parties, yet God unites all in the Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>O how some would be lifted up, if they could make a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:173134:44"/>of Gods Judgments, and that God should be the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner of their Revenges; If this Sickness should take parts, and go onely on one side! But the Just and Holy God finds sin in all, and visits all; God agrees us in our Sufferings. And the truth is, he may bless it to the uniting of us more than we are, since he makes no difference in the punishment of us. If this be a Judgment, this side hath displeased God as well as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Is it a Fatherly chastise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Why, then God takes care of the other Party as well as of theirs.</p>
               <p>I knew one once, that upon difference in Judgment, had been at some heats and distance with another Worthy man: It hapned
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:173134:44"/>shortly, that he fell Sick of a distemper that was Epidemick, as this is now; and he heard at the same time, that he with whom he differed, was down of the same distemper; And it is not to be said, how his heart was melted towards him, and how little the difference between them was in his eye, when both were under the same affliction. When Children will quarrel, and will not be quiet in the House, the wise Father beats them both, and it is the best way to agree them. O to what heighth, and distance, and to the destruction of Christian love, are our dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences risen! And all about, comparatively, little things. And we may know what weight the matter is of, by what these things are to us when Sick. Alas, a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:173134:45"/>Sick man sees these are far from the great things that his Soul is taken up with at such a time. How do carnal prejudices fall at such a time? How we can pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty one another, and can be glad of the Prayers of them that can Pray, of what perswasion soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And if I can but be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given my self, I shall freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give my brother, and desire to be forgiven by him too. O how charitable are we on our Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds? I wish we never let those heats kindle, which Sickness does so extinguish. One may be heard sure, among the Sick of the divided Parties to say, <hi>Who art thou that condemnest thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> If God will accept thee, thou wilt cease to judge thy brother any more. Sickness will find thee something else to do,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:173134:45"/>than to hate and revile, and censure any one for lesser things. And may this peaceable Spirit increase, and ever dwell with us. And if our being joined together in this common corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction unite us not, it is well if some greater Judgment come not upon us, that shall effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually agree us. One might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most venture our whole Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies to the sense and arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not so much of the most learned and most judicious, but of the Afflicted and Sick of both Sides.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>God makes sad breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Hopeful</hi> and <hi>useful</hi> persons are snatcht away. It is the Lords hand; men do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, that oft <hi>such men are taken away from the evil to come.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 57.1, 2.</note>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:173134:46"/>
                  <hi>There are skulls in Golgotha of all sizes,</hi> as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is. Indeed when they are gone, they were so useful, and so lovely, and so delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and so greatly taking, that we are ready to blame our selves, that we did not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see they were not like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.38.</note>
                  <hi>The world indeed was not worthy of them.</hi> But many bad ones are also gone in as great a surprise; Hopeful, as well as less promising persons in their Places, and the like Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances; That we should be further instructed in the sacred secrets of the Divine Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Providence; and <hi>that all things come alike to all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.1, 2.</note>
                  <hi>and that love or hatred is not to be known by any thing under the sun.</hi> The World is rid of some
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:173134:46"/>bad ones, and is punished in the loss of good ones: But Gods Will be done. We are to <hi>seek unto God,</hi> and unto him to resign <hi>the whole cause.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 102.23, 24.</note> It is not the first time he hath <hi>brought down mens strength in the way, and shortened</hi> [hopeful and useful] <hi>mens days. In the way,</hi> when to their thinking they were but entring on bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness, not near their Journeys end. Like some men that go from home, and dye in their Journey; that go to Sea, and dye in the Voyage. It is his will, and it is well it should be so. I have read a Story of a hopeful young man, that was found dead in his Study, with his Finger upon that place in <hi>Wisdom,</hi> 4.7, 8, &amp;c. <hi>For tho the righteous be prevented with death; yet shall he be in rest.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:173134:47"/>For honourable age is not that which standeth in length of time, nor that is measured by number of years. But wisdom is the gray-hairs unto men, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spotted life is old age. He pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God, and was beloved of him, so that living amongst sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners he was translated. Yea spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily was he taken away, lest that wickedness should alter his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, or deceit beguile his soul. For the bewitching of naughtiness doth obscure things that are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, and the wandering of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscence doth undermine the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mind. He being made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in a short time, fulfilled a long time. For his soul pleased the Lord, therefore hasted he to take him away from among the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> A very full and satisfactory account of such a Providence.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:173134:47"/>
                  <hi>Simlerus,</hi> a famous <hi>German</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, dyed young: the Author that writ his Life, hath this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark; That good and profitable men oft dye sooner than the wicked and unprofitable; and God may do it,</p>
               <p>To shew (1.) his displeasure and hatred to the World, not to let such live to do them good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His love to the good, to take them to himself.</p>
               <p>I confess, I met with an hint of this ensuing similitude from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which I think may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in many particular cases, wherein we think some are imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely taken away.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:173134:48"/>
               <p>A Child may be command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to go to bed before the rest of his Fellows. They may sit up to be merry, but he must go in the beginning or midst of the sport or business; for such indeed is our life, that when we are in the midst of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, and business, the call to Bed must be obeyed. Nor is the case hard:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> It may be, <hi>it is the Childs time;</hi> the Mother says, Come Child, it is your time. And when the time is come, I must break off in the midst, and leave others to their work or play.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It may be <hi>the Child is toiled;</hi> and tho not sensible of it, the Parent is. Come Child,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:173134:48"/>thou hast had a sore day of it, of Work or Travel, and I would have thee at thy rest; and when the Child comes to Bed (tho not altogether so willingly) he finds it easie, and better by far than sitting up any longer. <hi>For rest is sweet to the labouring man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 5.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It may be <hi>the Child is not all out well,</hi> and the sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting late up, may add to his Disease. Thou art lately reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, or hardly recovered, and nothing worse than sitting up late for one that is not well. Thou hast a diseased Soul, which longer sitting up may hurt, and sleep may cure. It is best for some to dye soon, to get perfectly cured, and worse Diseases prevented.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:173134:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It may be <hi>the Child do's no good,</hi> and do's but take up a Room, and hinder others, that may do some good with staying up. I am an useless Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and rather troublesome, and I cannot go to Bed too soon. Others may sit up, for they do somewhat w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>o Fire and Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. It should never grieve me to dye, that have but little left me to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It may be <hi>the Child is wrangling and unpeaceable.</hi> Get to Bed, unless you can be quiet. It is the wrangling of some that makes them pack sooner to Bed.
<note n="*" place="margin">Melanchthon <hi>said, He should dye willingly, that he might go away from the</hi> Sophistry <hi>of those times. And</hi> Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilius <hi>said, I desire to dye.</hi> 1. <hi>That I may enjoy the sight of the Son of God.</hi> 2. <hi>That I may be freed.</hi> Ab ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus &amp; implacabilibus odii, Theologorum. <hi>And another</hi> German <hi>Divine said,</hi> Quis me tandem li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berabit ab ista rixosâ Theologiâ.</note> And some that <hi>are wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with,</hi> and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have quietness, are sent to bed, that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:173134:49"/>they may be at quiet. Child, thy Step-Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will be quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling with thee; thou wouldst be at peace. I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted the tenderness of thy Spirit; <hi>thou hatest strife, and they hate peace.</hi> I have ordered thy Bed to be made ready, and laid down for thee. For shelter Child, go thou to Bed, and leave them to wrangle it out that love wrangling, and love to sit up to have their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>angle out.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>As good go to bed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.6. Mat. 25.5.</note>
                  <hi>as sleep by the fire.</hi> Some are <hi>dead whilst they live, others oft slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and sleep.</hi> Have such dead and sleepy fits, that it is better
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:173134:50"/>for them by far they were in Bed. Better dye than live to sin, and overlive our activeness and life in Religion.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>They that tarry, may set up to little purpose.</hi> It is not so good business in this World, that I should refuse rest to tarry by it.</p>
               <p>Eightly, <hi>They must all go to Bed anon.</hi> It is but a little time that I could stay up; It is no great difference in going a little sooner. To Bed I must go, and the sooner I go, the more rest I shall have.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, <hi>However my father bids me.</hi> And a good ordered Child never asks any questions, but obeys, and goes, when bidden.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:173134:50"/>
               <p>Tenthly, If a Child <hi>go to bed in the dark, and his bed be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;</hi> It is all one when he is in it, as if he had been lighted unto it. But if he <hi>have a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to Bed</hi> with him, he may go more comfortably. God will lighten thy darkness; and if thou have the light of his Countenance to go to Bed with, it is better than sitting up with the longest, and going to Bed, it may be, in the dark at last.</p>
               <p>Some live a great deal in a little time; when their work is done, they shall be called home, and the sooner the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. If some get their Work done sooner, why should they not be set at Liberty? <hi>Cleobis</hi> and <hi>Biton,</hi> the two Sons that drew their Mother in her Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:173134:51"/>when the Horses were not ready, and she should go to her Devotion: She is reported by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> to have asked of the Goddess, <hi>the greatest good for her Sons,</hi> and that Night they both dyed. The Heathens thought this an answer to her desires. Sure then Christians may much more make the greatest good out of Death. The same wise Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could say of one dying soon, <hi>He is departed the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet before drunkenness,</hi> before he came to the follies and vanities his after Age might have brought to him. O! but he might have done a great deal of good, if he had lived.</p>
               <p>Answer <hi>First,</hi> He might also have met with a great deal of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:173134:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> He might have met with many temptations to sin, which now he is past and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from. Better dye to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, than repent to recover from, sin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God will want no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of any good, that he will have done in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> And Heaven is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to him on his account, than any good he could have had, or any good he could have done, if he had tarried here. He is prevented with early Glory, and is not that well? Persons usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally can be willing to part with their dearest Children into the remotest parts of the World, upon their probable or likely advantage, tho they may never
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:173134:52"/>see them again; And shall any undervalue Heaven, so as not to think that a Preferment Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminent, so that they may afford to spare the sight of them for it? Parents can say, We must deny our selves for our Childrens good.— Ay, but a great comfort of our Life is gone; we would never have parted with him for any advantage; we needed not to let him go out of our sight; we had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to live together. But alas, you must dye your selves shortly, and then that is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered. You would not care how soon he came after you, and the matter is not so much that he is gone a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:173134:52"/>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>God orders sickness longer to some than to others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First, <hi>Some few get sooner through than others do.</hi> And if they part with their Sickness, before they have parted with their sin, it will be never the better for them. The shortest Sickness did not come without a cause, nor without a design from God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee; and thou mayest ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect an after-reckoning, if the Distemper went before thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentedst. There may be as much cause of, and displeasure in a short Sickness, as in a longer. <hi>O let the goodness of God</hi> (as well as thy afflicton) <hi>lead thee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> and let his tenderness of thee, melt, and not harden thee.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:173134:53"/>
               <p>Secondly, Some, <hi>if they escape, are brought very low, and they continue in long weakness.</hi> God sadly <hi>changes their countenance, tho yet he sends them not away.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 14.20.</note> They look like (that they might have been) even dead men. O that they may never set a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance on their sin any more. God hath kept thee long to it, it is well if thou hast yet learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy lesson. That he hath seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed so unwilling to let thee go, it is well if thou hast answered his leisure, and yielded thy self to him of all this long time. If thou be released, and not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged fairly, he hath thee within his reach, and at an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant can fetch thee in again. Suspect thy self, lest thou hast not been so yielding as thou shouldest have been, that he
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:173134:53"/>hath continued his hand so long upon thee. And beware of the sad consequence of being <hi>no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter after a long Sickness;</hi> and tremble at Hell, where the fit will never go off, and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment never end. And be sure to make out, what hitherto thou art wanting, in serious and spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy after Repentance.
<note place="margin">Eze. 14.23.</note>
                  <hi>And know that without a cause the Lord hath not done all this unto thee.</hi> Thou hast not had one fit more, nor been Sick one day longer, than thou didst deserve, or was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to thy Souls cure: And this thou hadst best see to, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less thou hast not felt enough of Gods hand; for he will not be baffled by thee. Men fall Sick again, not only by relapse, as to their distemper; but for not forsaking their sin by what they
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:173134:54"/>have had. A distemper tarries, as if loath to leave; and seems to be gone, and comes back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, which you call a <hi>Relapse.</hi> Alas, it tarries for something not yet effected in thee, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y Relations, and those that are afflicted with thee; and it comes again for something that is left behind, something that is not surrendred as it should be, and must be. Nothing of the thing it self, or of the continuance, or of the return, <hi>is out of the dust;</hi> but designed and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the least circumstance, and is to be answered by us, as thus by Infinite Justice, Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Faithfulness ordered upon us. But,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Some <hi>have continued weakness;</hi> distempers for years,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:173134:54"/>Chronical diseases, tedious and painful, and it may be incurable. And it may be they are puzled to understand why it should be so with them. Why it is of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="1">1st. Thou art apt to think thy case strange and singular; Alas it is no new thing, nor new method that God hath treated men in. <hi>Isaac</hi> above forty years blind. <hi>David</hi> at last bed-rid. <hi>Asa</hi> diseased in his feet, possibly of the painful Gout. How was <hi>Job</hi> stricken in his body, after he had lost all his goods besides? What Chronical diseases did <hi>Christ</hi> cure, of Leprosie, Palsie, Lunacy, eighteen-years-old In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And there is worse abroad than thine, even now. To have some eminent above
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:173134:55"/>many, for Piety, Charity, Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick usefulness, sweetness of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, laid aside under an uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable deprivation for his last years. To have others lye bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid in continued pain night and day, and clouded inwardly all the while, and but scarcely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for outwardly, and this for many years too; and the sad cases of deep continued me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, distraction, and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, shews a case harder than thine.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. It might be worse in it self, it might be without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission; it might be with thee as it is with the worst that can be found; and it might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with thee as it is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. Thy intermissions and breathing times, are of great
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:173134:55"/>clemency and compassion towards thee; and that thou hast not the addition of desertion, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and uncomfortable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to top it up with, is a great mercy.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly. Be it that there is no cure for it; but that it is the messenger that is sent for thee, and is like to attend thee as thy keeper, till thou art fetcht home;
<note place="margin">2 Chnro. 16.12.</note> What of all this? <hi>Asa</hi> sinned, in that <hi>he sought not the Lord, but to the physician.</hi> Not as if it were unlawful to seek to the Physician; but it is a sin not to seek to God first; or to look that the Physician should do good without God; and so to be vext, that the Physician can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not cure thee, is, as if God was not lookt at by thee. <hi>Is he in Gods
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:173134:56"/>stead?</hi> (to allude to that of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob) who hath denied</hi> health un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee?
<note place="margin">Gen. 32.2.</note> Will nothing content thee but curing?</p>
               <p n="1">1st. It may keep thee under long thoughts of Death before it come, so that thou canst not say but thou hast warning.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. It may keep thee out of sin and vanity, and withhold thee from some lusts, (which <hi>war against the soul</hi>) which some others of a better state of health, are forced to fight hard with, or be overcome by.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly. It may cure the sin and sloth of thy Soul. Thou car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riest the rod stuck to thy back. God keeps thee in awe, seems to resolve he will break thee of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:173134:56"/>thine humour, or he will know why. That as fear of a fit may keep thee in awe as to thy diet, and such things as are nought for thy distemper, thou dost care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully forbear; Thy passion, and pride, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is also nought for it, and thy distemper may so awe thee from thy wonted extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies, that thou mayest happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being thus held to it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract an habit of seriousness and meekness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to thy great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly. It may make thee more attentive unto God, more true at Ordinances, more trembling at his word. I confess I have for some time with sorrow of heart, seen how few take any great heed to the word Preached; but here and there a person under
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:173134:57"/>Affliction, that are of sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Spirits, that are broken o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise; these seem to give most heed, and are most affected with what is said. Thou hast the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of such a condition, and may God give thee the benefit of it.</p>
               <p n="5">5thly, This may wean thee from the World. Thou hast a good weaning-time, that thy parting will not be all at once. It is some preparation for Death, that there is nothing in this World of enjoyment, but what <hi>I can leave for God,</hi> and nothing of my care (as to Children and the like) <hi>but what I can leave to God.</hi> Thou hast now time to train up thy heart to this, which may make Death easie, as well as thy pain makes it desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:173134:57"/>
               <p n="6">6thly, Thou hast a brave time to get assurance; imploy this busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to purpose; cry mightily for it, and pursue it, till Truth and Mercy answer thee. O health well parted with, if it hath helped to inward peace, and assurance of Gods favour to thee! Thou hast nothing else to do, when thus enfeebled and cast aside, and <hi>set alone</hi> so long as thou hast been; and if this be the fruits of it at last, thou wilt bless God for this way of afflicting.</p>
               <p n="7">7htly. Thy work is Patience, to exercise and train thy Soul by degrees, to quietness and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedness with thy condition; to have thy will conquered, and thy self resigned to the Will of God; Not to desire to be otherwise than what God sees good and best for
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:173134:58"/>thee. To think it well and best it should be thus, because he hath ordered it thus to be. A brave Soul that was, of whom I have been certainly told, that when vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visited by some friends, he was found leaning against the corner of a Table upon a cushion, thrust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself with all his strength, and had no ease whilst he did not keep that posture: And he said, That if God would have it so, he could be patient with that posture as long as he lived. It is all one, says the well disciplin'd Soul, what my condition is, if God be with me at present, and will save my Soul at last.</p>
               <p n="8">8thly. We have received good, why should we not receive evil? I have this great affliction, but to purge out the dregs of pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:173134:58"/>It is common for the bottom of the glass to run dregs. Others die all at once, and I die by degrees, which may make it more easie at last. And if thy condition be singular, (which it may be it is not neither) that thou art more afflicted than some others; Conclude not, That it is because <hi>God loves thee less;</hi> but it may be, <hi>because thou wert worse</hi> than some others, and didst need more; and therefore be more humbled, if more afflicted. Or, God <hi>may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to make thee better</hi> than others, to make thee more mortified, humble, patient, Heavenly-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than others are, that are not in the like circumstances. But be patient, and thankful, and more holy, and all is well, and best for all this: And thou wilt say at last, That of all this sorrow thou
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:173134:59"/>couldst not have spared one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of it. And since we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways sinning, and provoking God to be sending to us; I had as good keep the Messenger with me, which I know and am used to, as to have fresh and strange ones sent to me every day. — For thee to say after all, That it is thy greatest trouble, and thou art cast down under sickness, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it disables thee for work; It is a great failing.</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>For (as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> says) 1. For thy personal advantage, it doth most quicken to such duties; for Praying and Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now or never,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For others, It is not thy duty when God disables thee for it. If he lay thee aside in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:173134:59"/>the Vineyard, and doth thy work by others, he doth thee no wrong: He doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire work of thee, when thou canst not do it. But see what deceitfulness lies in this, when we have time, and health, and opportunity to work, then we loyter; and when we are Sick and disabled, then we complain we cannot work.</p>
               </q>
               <p>That thou art a trouble to others to attend thee, it is a weak complaint; If thou art not counted so to thy Relations, thou shouldest be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for it, and own Gods kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to thee, that they are tender of thee, and count nothing too much, or enough that they can do for thee. And it is their duty to be tender of thee; It is part of their work which God calls them to, to look to thee. He
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:173134:60"/>will reward thy Tenders for what they do for thee, and would have thee well lookt to. And it is all one what is their work, all goes into the account of the Lords service; and it tries their patience, and natural affection, and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and compassion, and painful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and will be their great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and shall have a full recompence.</p>
               <p>The last <hi>ƲSE</hi> is,</p>
               <p>To those <hi>that have had breaches made upon them</hi> by this Affliction. Some very sad and surprizing; why, the Lord hath done it. And that you should not sorrow to excess,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.9. Jer. 31.15.</note>
                  <hi>or after the world,</hi> to weep <hi>like Rachel, and refuse to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted.</hi> Besides, the comfort you should take in the hoped for hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness of them that are gone, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:173134:60"/>that you should not say, <hi>you have lost</hi> (as one says), but you have onely <hi>parted</hi> with them; so as in Christian hope and confidence, you shall meet them again. I would suggest, to stop the present sorrow by way of diversion, these two important intimations. Is thy Relation gone?</p>
               <p>First, <hi>Art thou ready?</hi> It is a seasonable Prayer upon the fresh tidings of this and that friend that is gone; <hi>The Lord grant the next may be ready.</hi> But let it not seem uncompassionate and harsh in thy present grief, to ask thee that question. This is a momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous inquiry, and thou that art left, must go, and it may be soon. If thou be ready, bless God, and rejoyce in the mercy, that thou hast good hopes to meet thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:173134:61"/>in glory shortly, and let that suffice. If not ready, make it thy speedy business; and instead of sorrowing, where sorrow can do no good, fall to thy own tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous concernment, and let fear and danger take up thy grief, and find thy Soul other work.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>May this be the worst?</hi> It is a great Affliction. Now as our Saviour said,
<note place="margin">Joh 5.14.</note>
                  <hi>Behold, thou art made whole, sin no more, lest a worse thing come unto thee.</hi> So I, Behold, thou art sadly and sharply afflicted, and the Lord hath sadly wounded, and broken thee, <hi>sin no more, lest a worse thing come unto thee.</hi> Wrath is begun, meet thy God, do not think he hath done his worst. Search for sin, that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:173134:61"/>hath brought this evil upon thee, and repent, to prevent a worse. <hi>Let thy sorrow be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God, to work repentance.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note> That this sorrowful Providence, may not be a Presage and forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a greater mischief. But being sanctified and improved this way, it may prevent such a thing, and thou maist escape with this.</p>
               <p>And thou mayest make this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advantage of the Death of thy Relation, To follow him with thy profitable thoughts into the state he is in.</p>
               <p>First, <hi>For his Soul.</hi> O think of Heaven the more for his sake, who is newly gone thither. O think what a change he has found. What a blessed state of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:173134:62"/>Life, and Light, and Love, and Praise, he is entred into! How he is transformed and perfected in his entrance <hi>among the spirits of just men made perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">He. 12.23. Ma. 22.30.</note> and is made one among them; like <hi>an Angel of God.</hi> When <hi>Esther</hi> was taken into the Court, in likelihood of such high Preferment, <hi>Mordecai</hi> (her dear Uncle) <hi>walked every day before the Court,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Est. 2.11.</note>
                  <hi>to know how Esther did, and what should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of her.</hi> And so such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned Relations upon the high advance of theirs, should walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Court of Heaven daily, to contemplate of what is become of them. What a dignity they are in, of Blessedness, Holiness, and Immortality. How their wants, and desires, and fears, are all ended, and what perfect Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness they are commenc't up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on!
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:173134:62"/>That now <hi>they are made like unto Christ,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 3.2.</note>
                  <hi>and shall see him as he is.</hi> O how do they admire Rich and Free Grace, that hath saved such sinners as they were! And how do they adore and love Christ, for what he hath done for them from first to last? And how they do live in the concordant praises of the Blessed Deity, their Creator, Redeemer, and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier, and shall do so to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity! O joyn thy Soul to them in the same work, of Love and Thanksgiving, as much as thou canst; which may be a foretast to thee of what thou shalt have, and a blessed pledge and earnest to thee, That thou also shalt at last be with them. And let it further thy Preparations, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease thy Desires and Longings for it. They have now been so
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:173134:63"/>many days, or weeks, or months in Glory: Let these thoughts raise thy Soul above all these things, and make thee take wing for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to be with Christ, which is far better. And</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>For his Body.</hi> O think now how that body is laid into darkness, and how far by this time it is gone unto corruption? <hi>Lazarus</hi> was counted <hi>to stink</hi> when he had been <hi>dead but four days.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 11.39.</note> O how his beauty is consumed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way! How hath he found his kindred under ground, <hi>corruption his father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 17.14. John 11.35, 38.</note>
                  <hi>and the worms his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and sister!</hi> Our Saviour <hi>wept,</hi> and <hi>groaned</hi> over <hi>Lazarus</hi> when in the grave: It could not be for the loss of him, because he knew he would raise him again at that instant. But it was (as Divines
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:173134:63"/>think) from his sense he had of what sin by Death had brought upon man, that his body should thus be subject to such destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, stench, and rottenness, and loathsomeness, that was ere while so beautiful and lovely. <hi>Camera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> tells a story, That in a Town of <hi>Germany,</hi> there was a young Gentleman, one of the fairest young men of his time; but when taken with a grievous Sickness, of which he dyed, his Friends im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portun'd him, that he might be taken in Sculpture or Picture, to be his memorial to posterity; He would not grant it. All they could obtain was, That after he had been dead, and some days in the ground, they should open his grave, and represent him as they then found him. They did so, and found his face half gnawn away
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:173134:64"/>with worms, and about his mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff and back bone, they found ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Serpents. They caused this spectacle as they found it, to be cut in stone, and it lyes among the armed Statues of his Ancestors; and the Author says, he had oft seen it. O how should this hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us, and make us for ever abhor priding our selves in any bodily beauty! It was good Counsel given to one, that looked a good face in the glass; O think how that face would look, if you could see it one year after it had been in the grave. And yet think also of the Resurrection, which is the Christian relief against this inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table misery of corruption; <hi>That when Christ comes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Thes. 4.14. Phil. 3.21.</note>
                  <hi>those that sleep in Jesus, God will bring with him. And these vile bodies shall be made like to his glorious body, according
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:173134:64"/>to the working, whereby he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to subdue all things to himself.</hi> Even Death, and Corruption, and all. Adore and believe this Doctrine of the Resurrection: And thus live with the deceas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with their Souls in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and their bodies in the grave, for thy Souls Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>It is now time to conclude this Discourse: And upon the whole matter, I shall do it with the excellent advice of a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy man.</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>Pray for the first Grace of Gods Children, Not to need to be corrected.</p>
                  <p>Or for the second, To be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the least correction; A
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:173134:65"/>sign of a melting heart, to bleed at the least blow.</p>
                  <p>Or at least, Thirdly, That God would not let us go so far, as that neither Prosperity nor Adversity can do us good. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:173134:65"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>